Welcome to an Introduction to Retrieval Augmented
Generation or RAG for short.
Before we dive intowhat RAG is, we need to first discuss the
common shortcomings of generative languagemodels.
Generative language models have pickedup quite a bit of traction and use cases since2002 with the advent of ChatGPT.
Their ability toanswer questions and complete tasks with a simpleprompt
makes them incredibly useful.
However, thesedigital helpers are not without limitations.
One common issue is hallucinations.
Imagine asking, "Whenwere the Pyramids of Giza moved across the GoldenGate Bridge for the second time?
And the languagemodel confidently answering, "the Pyramids of Gizawere moved for the second time in 1856."
Whileobviously wrong, this behavior makes sense asLLMs original purpose was to predict the nexttoken in a sequence,
not factually answer userquestions.
Making matters worse, chatbots don'tattribute their knowledge.
By default, ChatGPTdoes not cite any external knowledge sources whenit makes factual claims, we'd have to verify theinformation, ourselves.
Additionally, knowledge cut-offs can leave them outdated.
For instance, askinga chatbot to write Next dot js code might result inthe syntax of an older version of the framework, despite significant changes in recent releases.
For example, GPT 3.5 has a knowledge cut-off ofJanuary, 2002.
Another limitation is ContextWindow Size. If we want a model to
answerquestions based on a lengthy document,
pastingthe entire document into the prompt might notwork.
Cutting-edge models are improving in this
area but larger prompts translate to higher costs.
On the other hand, smaller models, while more
affordable, remain limited by their context size.
Fortunately, a technique called RetrievalAugmented Generation or RAG, offers solutionsto these problems.
RAG essentially grants LLMsaccess to external knowledge sources.
This canreduce hallucinations, enable the consultation of
your own sources, and keep the LLM's knowledge up todate.
The external sources which RAG retrieves toaugment the model's generations can be documents, databases, or even a live search of the internet.
But for this course, we'll focus on documents,which are among the simplest and most common usecases.
And RAG is more than a method of shoring upthe weak points of LLMs.
It also represents a newway to think about their functionality.
Instead ofstoring information about the world inside the LLM's
weights, RAG makes it possible to store knowledgeoutside of the model,
freeing up the model itselfto focus on reasoning and cognition,
while theretrieved knowledge source functions more like
a database in traditional software.
At its core,RAG relies on embeddings which are rich numerical
representations of meaning derived usually fromtext chunks.
However, they can also be made of othermodalities,
such as image or audio.
These embeddingscapture the relationships
between different partsof the text.
When the user asks a question, thequestion is converted into an embedding and iscompared to the document embeddings, retrievingthe most relevant information.
This is commonlyreferred to as semantic search.
These results arethen injected into a prompt to the language model, which can reason about them, summarize them, andshare them with the user.
RAGs applications arevast. It can handle nonpublic information, likebusiness documents,
create a long-term memoryfor chatbots by embedding past conversations, and facilitate verifiable research by providingsource attribution.
Additionally, RAG can unearthspecific information not
well-represented in the LLM's training data.
Now that we've covered what RAG is
and where it fits in the LLM landscape,
the restof this course will dive further into what
we'vediscussed previously and more.
According to ouragenda, the next lesson should be Introduction toEmbeddings and Similarity Search for approximately5 minutes,
followed up with a Search with Chromaexercise.
Then we'll go into Document Chunkingwith RAG for approximately 7 minutes, along withan associated exercise.
Then, we'll dive into PromptEngineering for RAG for about 6 minutes,
followedup with its associated exercise.
Then, we'llhave a review exercise, and finally a quiz.